Leah: So, what are the strengths and
weaknesses of Waterfall and when should
it be used over other methodologies?
Chris: The Strengths are it’s easy to
use and manage -Waterfall is very easy
to use and learn as it is a linear
approach which runs from one stage to
the next until the project is complete.
Each stage has certain deliverables and a
review so the next stage wouldn’t happen
until that stage has been signed off.
Suitable for certain types of projects
that required a high degree of
predictability- As all the planning along
with strong supporting documentation
that occurs at the beginning of
a project, there is a high degree
of predictability which is more
suitable for large scale projects.
Discipline is built in-Each
project has specific start
and end points to the project.
It is at these points that the
client and stakeholders are involved.
The project isn’t started until the
requirements and design has been
signed off, so the deadlines and
requirements are likely to be met.
Documentation-One of the key
principles of ‘Waterfall’ is its
strong supporting documentation
which is required for each stage.
This supports the team and project,
less training requirements, supports
future projects and supplies details
to the stakeholders if needed.
Leah: However, the Weaknesses are it’s
Difficult to change- As Waterfall is
a linear approach it does not have the
flexibility of Agile as once a stage is
complete, it is difficult to go back.
Software delivered at end of production-As
the software/product is delivered at the
end of the production there is a risk that
it won’t meet stakeholder’s expectations.
Gathering accurate requirements can be
challenging-The first stage is crucial
and would need a Project Manager with
effective communication skills as this is
where the requirements from the customers
and stakeholders would be gathered.
A customer may not know what they want
until later on in the project and this
could cause issues in the process and
have an impact on the whole project.
Large projects which have dependencies
on external systems such as
hardware, and where the requirements
need to remain fixed with little
tolerance for failure [or bugs]
would use a Waterfall methodology.
Examples of this include ‘payment
gateways’, ‘military defence
systems’, ‘construction’, ‘flight
controls’, ‘manufacturing plants’ etc